I could definitely see a future, [music]
very scary future in which a lot of
people would not have meaningful work.
>> This is Darren Asimoglu, an MIT
economist and winner of the 2024 Nobel
Prize [music] in Economics. He thinks
we're overlooking some of AI's biggest
opportunities. So, where should we be
looking and what will keep us valuable?
I've seen a lot of posts where people
say, "Oh, instead of hiring someone, I
deployed an agent."
>> Automation is great. The problem is the
only thing we do is automation. that
will eliminate too many jobs without
creating meaningful high-paying high
productivity jobs to create new
opportunities for people.
>> So, what should people be doing? What
skills should they be acquiring?
>> If everybody wants my opinion, I [music]
would say go and study.
>> Thanks to HubSpot for sponsoring this
video.
So, you said something in 2024 that AI
would add about 1% to US GDP in the next
10 years with only 5% of tasks being
fully automatable. What do you think
about this now in 2026?
>> Well, first of all, it's my pleasure to
be here and I do not claim that I have
any unique insight into AI. AI is like
an elephant. Everybody is feeling a
different part of it. But I think I try
to bring a little bit of basic economic
calculus to the discussions of
productivity. And this was more than two
years ago.
There's a huge amount of uncertainty and
there is even more today. But there have
also been some very rapid developments
especially this year with agentic AI.
Probably now I would have put that
number a little higher than 5%. But I
still think that a lot of the discussion
exaggerates
how quickly we're going to see
automation because automation is hard.
Integrating automation into
organizations is hard. Diffusion of new
technologies
especially when they require lots of
complimentary investments and
adjustments is hard and slow. That
doesn't mean it's not a transformative
technology. It doesn't mean that we
cannot get benefits from it. But we have
to be grounded
in thinking about how quickly and how
uh thoroughly the economy is going to
change. And we still still have the same
discussion that we should have about
every technology. What's the best way of
using it? How
it could be misused and who will benefit
from it?
>> You mentioned agentic. Is there anything
you're when you see it, you'll think
okay now I can expand my figure to like
two digits. Uh when it comes to impact
of AI,
>> I think the advances in coding have been
really really rapid. What is it about
coding that makes it
so conducive to have the most rapid
advances of any occupation?
I think it's the fact that coding is
obviously done in offices. You don't
have any interaction with the real
world. the people who are supervising
coding are very very uh fluent in AI and
in technology in general but also and
this is a very important part just like
math just like chess coding has rules
something either runs or doesn't run
reinforcement learning is very effective
when you have a ground truth that says
no that's wrong I think in many
occupations we lack that customer
service I think most people would have
said customer service is going to be the
first
occupation to be fully automated by AI
and we're seeing some of it but it's
turning out to be very slow and very
difficult and most of the organizations
that I deal with their AI system is so
bad it's like a nightmare when I call
customer service and I get AI oh my god
it's going to be another 10 minutes
before somebody can actually help me and
that's because there's a social element
many of the things that you ask from
customer service change over time. They
are person specific. Different people
use different language for making the
same questions
and there are a lot of gray areas edge
cases. So that makes it much messier and
it will require humans to either either
oversee it or work with it or ideally a
much better collaboration so that AI
could be complimentary to humans. So all
of those are in play. Which ones we
choose is going to have a very important
impact. How many jobs are going to be
displaced? How much productivity effects
we're going to get? And who's going to
benefit from it?
>> With coding, we have deterministic
outcome that we can check easily with
customer service. It's much more
personalized as you mentioned. Do you
think in the future with stronger models
we'll be able to achieve it or it's just
the bottleneck of AI in general that it
can't function without a human in the
>> I would definitely not say there's this
one thing that AI will not be able to do
in the future. I think the last 10 years
have given us enough examples of
AI if you put enough resources enough
data can make progress on many things.
But the question is how fast and
[snorts] can it do so across all the
domains. If if I step back and I say if
you ask me why so little productivity
improvements and what can we do about it
and I would have just one word for my
vision of how we can improve the
economic effects of AI applications. We
just need much better and more
applications. And in some sense one can
make the argument and again I don't know
this this may be incorrect. Look I'm not
in anthropic inside the organization.
I'm not an open AI. I don't know what
they are learning in real time from
their experiments and the enormous
amount of resources and they're very
very talented people in all of these
organizations. But you can make the case
that the United States, Silicon Valley,
uh, is putting too much emphasis on
foundation models and not enough on
applications and not enough in
integrating applications into
organizations. So when I when you know
we're we're told all the time US is
ahead of China and indeed in large
language models that seems quite clear.
Chinese models are catching up
sometimes, but they are using the lead
of US models. There's some distilling
going on probably. But one thing that I
see Chinese companies do that I don't
see as much in the United States is
they're putting a lot of emphasis in
getting robotics, getting AI into the
production line. And one thing that they
are throwing at that problem is a huge
amount of engineering talent. The United
States doesn't seem to have that much
engineering talent and whatever we have
is all going into foundation models. you
touched upon such an interesting subject
cuz as an immigrant when I see things
how they work in the US and ask why is
it so and the reply is oh historically
as
>> oh no that's the only way to do it I
think here is one thing one other thing
I'll I'll say I don't want to make you
know overgeneralizations but I think as
a signpost
if there is one thing that's been not
good for us AI industry in my in my
opinion it's the inevitabilism
that the view that whatever we're doing
is the only way to do it. There's no
other way and if you're raising that
question, you're an idiot. So I
completely reject that there. I think AI
is a very versatile technology as are
all general purpose technologies, GPTs,
what economists
call things like electricity,
uh printing press, etc. which spawn a
lot of other applications. One thing we
know from history, one thing we've
learned from a lot of economics and uh
looking at previous examples, there are
so many different ways of developing
these general purpose technologies and
different ways are not neutral. They
bring different types of benefits. They
uh have different types of costs and
just thinking that whatever we're doing
is the only way or by far the best way I
think is a mistake. And I think another
problem that comes with it is
measurement, right? So how do you
measure the impact of AI on your
personal productivity, on your company's
productivity? And when I talked to Eric
Bjernson when they were doing this
study, they like the the economic impact
of AI was basically zero. We talked to
him in May.
>> So the raw capabilities are
skyrocketing, but the economic impact is
pretty muted right now. that gap between
the capabilities and what's actually
happening is a big opportunity I think.
>> Do you think there's a measurement
problem there as well?
>> He's a very very serious scholar and he
knows this industry pretty much better
than any other social scientist and I
think he's more optimistic than I am. So
if you ask him about the productivity
effects in 2035, 2034, which is what I
was writing about at the time, he would
have put it somewhat more aggressively.
But yeah, I think his conclusion is AI
is not having the kinds of productivity
effects we're we're expecting yet, but
it will, which is very much where I am
as well. We don't see it yet, but it
will, but it will be a little slower
than in my opinion than what Eric would
say. But but I I would be very very
happy if he's right and I think he's got
a much better chance of being right than
many other people in the industry who
are just overly optimistic about what's
going on.
>> How do you think we should measure in
fact of AI on organization or even
personal productivity?
>> Productivity has always been difficult
to measure and there's a quality issue.
I think one place where uh Eric has put
a lot of emphasis rightly is that
[snorts] in the digital age more broadly
over the last 40 years we don't know how
to measure quality and that might mean
that we are understating some
[clears throat] of the productivity
benefits of not just AI but computers in
general. I agree with that. The problem
is I think we didn't know how to measure
the per the quality improvements coming
from uh better cars or uh better
highways either. So there there always
been an issue of measuring quality.
>> I think it's the happiness measurement
like eventually just measure happiness
[laughter] if you want.
>> It is I mean that's that's also great. I
think well-being is a very important
thing there. I would be more negative
about AI and all the associated
technologies. is I think social media
has been horrendous for us. It has
damaged community. It has damaged
people's ability to deal with adversity
because we don't interact with people in
real social networks.
It has made our worst instincts more
salient because algorithms go after
rage, emotions, envy. So, I think it has
been horrible. I hope AI will not repeat
social media's mistakes.
>> Let's take a quick break here because
what Darren just said about technology
really stood out to me. AI can be used
simply to replace tasks and cut cost or
it can help people become more
productive and make better decisions. As
I see this all the time running two
companies and working with a big team,
every new AI tool promises to save time.
But adding more tools doesn't
automatically make your business more
efficient. If your marketing data is in
one place, sales is working somewhere
else and customer information is spread
across different systems, your team ends
up spending more time managing the tools
instead of actually using them. That's
what I like about HubSpot. It brings
marketing, sales, customer service, and
content together on one AI powered
customer platform. Your teams can work
from the same customer information at
every stage of the journey instead of
constantly switching between
disconnected systems. Each HubSpot
product is powerful on its own, but they
work even better together. So whether
you're building a company or trying to
make your existing team more effective,
you can start with the tools you need
and grow from there. You can explore
HubSpot and get started for free through
the link in the description. Thanks to
HubSpot for sponsoring this video. Let's
talk about workers sharing gains of this
new technology.
>> My favorite topic.
>> Yeah, you're particularly vocal about
it. So when you say we have these strong
models but we lack applications, is that
the education problem? Do you think we
still need a stronger model or what do
we need to see the impact of AI on our
day-to-day positive impact?
>> I think
existing models are already very capable
as a foundation upon which to build
applications.
There are so many things we can do
that
would be quite feasible with the
existing infrastructure. [snorts] Let me
mention a few examples.
Much better quality control very easy
with existing models. Tools for nurses.
We have a real health care crisis in
this country. We spend almost one out of
every $5 on healthare. And look at the
outcomes. There are real public health
challenges. There are real bottlenecks
in the healthcare industry. Imagine
nurses can be more involved in the care
process in diagnosis,
prescription,
decisions about patient well-being. And
one big barrier for that is quality
control and information. those can be
very very easily supplied by existing AI
models with the right applications built
on top of our current uh
models. Yeah, I think you probably need
to train nurses a little differently. So
there's a human capital aspect that's
going to go complimentary to that. But
the bottleneck isn't the human capital
of the nurses. The bottleneck is the
application. The bottleneck is the tech
industry not doing it. Teachers, same
thing. electricians. We can give so much
better tools to electricians. It's just
like a such an easy lowhanging fruit.
Many blue color tasks can be made much
more effective with AI. We're seeing
some of them in China. Again, why are we
not doing that in the United States? So,
this is the bottleneck isn't the
foundation models. The bottleneck I mean
even last year's models would have been
good enough for most of the things that
we could do.
>> A lot of it sounds like a great business
opportunity.
>> It is. It is
>> AI for electricians.
Electric. This is such a huge market.
Again, discovered after I moved here,
how much those people are making, how
much you pay uh for a small
>> and there's such a shortage of
electricians.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And uh you wait three 3 weeks for the
most basic task and then electrician
comes and says, "Oh, no. This new
machinery, I can't deal with it."
>> Why not? Because I've never seen it
before.
>> And this is where AI comes in.
>> This is where AI comes in. It's just
such an easy problem. When it comes to
teachers and healthcare, do you think
it's a government problem or there's
still opportunity for companies?
>> Well, I think healthcare and education
is a two-way street or three-way street
because most healthcare dollars have
involvement from the government one way
or another. Teachers too. So, so yeah, I
think the government could play an
important role. But for electricians,
blue collar workers, for customer
service representatives, for scientists,
that's the private sector, mostly the
private sector. So I said three-way
because even when you take the
government out, there are two parties,
the tech companies and the management of
the business that we're talking about.
So both need to [snorts] be on board. In
my own conversations with CEOs of
leading companies or high level managers
of leading companies, when I mention
what I call proworker AI, AI that will
make workers more productive, they say,
"This is exactly what we need. We're on
board with it." Do they mean it? I don't
know. I can't test because the tools are
not being supplied by tech companies.
When I mention the same thing to people
from tech companies, they either nod and
turn their head or they say, "You live
in a different world. We're going to
create AGI. What are you talking about?"
>> They're worried about something that's
way ahead versus something they can fix
now. When you mentioned something for
bluecollar workers and you mentioned
China, what are the good examples?
>> [snorts]
>> Several manufacturing companies I've
spoken to in China are integrating both
robotics and AI uh Foxcon BYD uh their
other uh AE EV producers. They're all
very teched up and one thing I see from
their experience is that it's a slow
process and they require more engineers
than they always think. Fortunately for
them, China has an enormous supply of
engineers.
>> What would be your advice to
entrepreneurs who are watching who are
choosing what to work on? How do they
choose the right niche? Because I think
from all of the podcasts I've been doing
recently, everyone keeps saying me
riches are in the niches, especially
with AI because opportunity lies in this
boring business which hasn't been
automated in the past 20 years. And
maybe still pen and paper, but if you
come in and you tackle that problem,
this is where the opportunity.
>> Absolutely. And uh the only thing I
would not have I would not have used the
word boring. I think it's very exciting.
Imagine
>> boring from outside sounds a lot more
>> I know. [laughter] I know. But that's
that's that's that's so wrong. First of
all, it is pie in the sky. Nobody can
even agree on the definition of AGI.
It's always in the future and it is
frankly speaking not a future that we
can fully imagine either. I mean if if
you really mean by AGI and then the ASI
artificial super intelligence machines
could do everything [clears throat]
everything that humans can do better
that seems quite far to me but it seems
also very dystopian I mean there won't
be even any jobs for the best physicists
the best mathematicians the best social
communicators AI will do everything
better so what I don't understand
there's so many like inconsistencies in
the public debate on AI one of them is
people they say, "Oh, AGI is great. It's
going to come soon, but we're going to
also have lots of things for humans to
do." That can't be. If you mean anything
serious by AGI or ASI,
there can't be that many things left for
humans.
>> I wanted to dig a little deeper into the
practical use of AI today. So, when you
mention uh that business opportunity,
the researchers, how do you use AI in
your daily research and what can be
done?
>> I must say I am behind the frontier. I
use AI for background research and I
have increasingly over this year
started consulting AI for criticism of
uh things I write and ideas I have
>> which is very interesting because when I
first experimented with this with chat
chat GPT 3.5 and then chat GPT4 I
thought it was very disappointing and
now it's so much better. I also
encourage all of my students and
research assistants to set up an AI
infrastructure for their research and uh
and sort of as support for what they do,
never to replace them. I discourage
people uh even people who have English
as a second language from using AI to
write for them because I think people
should be in charge of their own
writing. But I encourage every student
who's a second not a native speaker of
English to use AI as as a correction
like run it through AI and see where
your sentences don't make sense or are
too long or are non- grammatical. So I
think there's a lot of mundane uses of
AI already as very very good and there
are lots of things but I have I very
much worry about a different kind of
loss of control which is that we
collectively but especially as students
and learners delegate too much to AI so
that we don't flex our mental muscles
and we don't engage in learning. That is
I think a first order issue. I see that
a lot with students from studies that I
think the use of AI has been pretty
disastrous in K through 12 education
because we've done it blindly
without guardrails. I said that actually
in 2024 also or 2023
that it was a dangerous
huge social experiment to unleash
generative AI on schools without any
guard rails all at the same time.
because we didn't know what it was going
to do and I don't think it has my worst
fears have come to pass but it's been
pretty close to that. When do you need
to say to yourself, okay, I'm going to
stop here and I need to think by myself
when it comes to this issue and just use
AI maybe to
>> yeah I mean because for me it's like
different first of all I'm from a
different generation unfortunately and
second I just love thinking I love
taking pen and paper and sketching
things out so in fact I have to prompt
myself
run this through AI I have never used
for example AI to do math
>> I should I mean AI is much better than
me in math. But I like doing the math
myself. When I write down models or when
I do calculations, I do them by hand
because that's what I'm used to and I
can do it fast and I can learn
something. I learned something from my
mistakes. But I'm sure if I step back, I
could do more.
>> When you do math by yourself, do you
ever think about this? It was the
calculator problem because teachers were
protesting against the calculator. Now
we still use it everywhere and it sped
up the complexity of things that we can
solve. Do you think AI is going to
enable us to do that or because it's
taking away in general our critical
thinking we won't be able to progress
further?
>> I worry about the latter. I think the
analogy to the calculator is useful but
you have to do it carefully. The
calculator could only take over some
very very very small part of it. And I
know of nobody who used the calculator
to sort of do thinking for them. And I
know of no school ever that said to
students, "Now you have a calculator,
you don't learn how to multiply." I
mean, there were calculators when I was
a student.
>> We all learned how to multiply, how to
divide. And I can't imagine not knowing
that. That is such an important building
block for many other things. Same thing
for differentiation. Like if you don't
know calculus,
how could you even take the next step?
>> Yeah. It's how far the skill goes. With
calculator, it's basically just this
function. with AI is the whole critical
thing.
>> It's the whole critical thinking and and
and the boundaries are very gray like
where do you stop in using AI? How do
you still [snorts] engage in the key
steps of human innovation and human
creativity together with AI?
>> One thing before we keep going. If you
want to stay updated on all the things
these founders say here, we take the use
cases and prompts from every
conversation and put them into my
newsletter called future proof. And of
course, we also put my own beautiful use
cases there. For example, we'll put
together the seven skills that came up
again and again, the ones people will
need in the next few years. These are
the skills that my team and I are also
using daily. Subscribe through the link
in the description. You'll get that one.
And you can also read our previous
newsletters and see what you missed.
Going back to businesses. So when you
look at all those posts on X where
someone's saying, you know, I haven't
seen a lot of like I fired my whole team
and hired agents, but I've seen a lot of
posts where people say, oh, instead of
hiring someone, I deployed an agent.
What do these companies and people miss
in the long term when they do that?
Because I know you're against marketing
agents as a replacement for a person.
Let me actually clarify
my stance on this. And this is based,
you know, on work I've done on robots,
[snorts] work I've done on early 20th
century technology, work I've done on
the industrial revolution, and
theoretical work I've done. I am not
against automation, nor do I think it's
possible to stop automation. We want
automation and anybody who wants to
reverse automation, I'm against that. We
don't want to go back to the days where
we carry heavy things on our backs,
automation is great. The problem is if
we the only thing we do is automation.
A, we're not going to get the full
productivity because it's not that easy
to do everything with automation. and B,
we're not going to create shared
prosperity because that will eliminate
too many jobs without creating
meaningful highpaying high productivity
jobs to create new opportunities for
people.
>> So my point has always been use
technology both for automation and other
things have a balanced approach and
digital technologies I have argued have
provided a lot of opportunities for
generating new things for humans to do
and it's doubly true with AI. So I want
AI to be used for automation so long as
we also use AI for creating new things
like for nurses, for electricians, for
many occupations we can't even dream
about right now.
>> How do you explain it to a small
business owner whose only metric is uh
increasing profits? What is the economic
downturn?
>> Productivity. Productivity I think again
and in my experience again it may be
cheap talk. People may [snorts] be nice
to me when I talk to them or I might
have fooled them but most businesses
actually get that. Not everybody, but
most of them get that your workers are
your greatest asset. Imagine making them
more productive. That's fantastic for
the business. And in fact, it's a better
calculus. Like imagine you have 100
employees and I tell you, you can
automate 5% of those jobs and reduce the
cost by half in those 5%. Or you can
make your workers 5% more productive.
The latter is going to get you much
more.
>> Oh, and your competitors are going to be
automating their workforce. And if
you're getting rid of people then your
productivity is going to eventually
>> right. I mean it's a it's
>> it's just your workers have a lot of
experience have a lot of some of them if
you have been a good at pass they have
commitment to the work to the to the to
the business. If you can make them more
innovative better at problem solving
better at doing new things that's the
kind of business that's going to
succeed. Let me ask you a question. What
are the companies? Which ones are the
companies from the past that you
remember? And you'll give me familiar
answers like Ford Motor Company, General
Motors, General Electric.
>> The first comes to mind,
>> you know, uh IBM,
>> Microsoft.
>> What's common about all of them did
something new. They didn't just cut
costs and take took what others were
doing. They imagined new markets, new
technologies, new tasks. Henry Ford
himself captured that. He said, "If I
had asked the consumers what they
wanted, they would have told me foster
horses." So that's what we need from
successful companies and cutting your
cost by 5%. That's not going to make you
go down the in the history books.
>> When it comes to automation, do you have
a rule on how do you know which task you
mentioned 5% of tasks are automatable.
How do you know when to automate
something or when it's not worth
automating? If you cut your cost by 5%,
GDP is typically going to go up by 5%
times your share of GDP. That's not
hard. The hard part is A, if you're
changing quality, that's a little bit
more complicated. And B, actually, even
if you're going to cut costs by 5%
in a number of years, it's going to take
you a lot of work to get there. And and
what I'm seeing from a few businesses
that I know is that they take the
automation plunge sometimes because they
think it's going to be easy, sometimes
because they think they're under
pressure, and then they can't make it
work because automation is not that
easy. You have to integrate into the
company. Now, many people have started
using the word AI has a jagged frontier.
I I like that image, but it's also a
code word for saying, oh, we
overestimated AI. It's much harder to do
it. And we thought we could lay off
workers because of AI. No, we can't. But
if you take that really seriously, it
means, oh, it's so jagged. I'm going to
keep more or less the same number of
workers and now I'm doing AI and it's
just a milange.
>> Yeah, it's just a lot more work from
businesses moving on to education. As
someone who's in academia, is university
still going to be worth a lot of money
in 10 years?
>> I think so. But let me preface that with
a few caveats.
First, I have never believed and I'm
even more convinced about this both for
economic and social reasons that
everybody should go to college. People
have diverse skills. They have different
interests. We should be engaged in
lifelong learning. But the traditional
liberal arts type education is not for
everyone. Nor do we want everybody to
have exactly the same perspective in
society. Second, a lot of what
university does, I'm afraid to say, is
also a signal. When you go to Harvard,
MIT, Stanford, you're also buying the
name. And that's good for you, not
necessarily that good for society. And
third, every university is understanding
now that they have to change their
business model. They have to change how
they deliver education. They are in
search of what types of skills they
should focus on. And my very very
superficial opinion is that universities
understand that. But you know what? The
same actually applies to high schools
and middle schools and they are not.
They're they're even further behind the
curve. One thing I've experienced in the
United States and is that many students
when they come to college are unprepared
and that is going to get worse and that
really will make colleg's business even
harder. I've seen that because I've you
know written a textbook for first years
in economics
how often weekly prepared students are
and how that's actually getting worse
over time even before AI. how many
colleges
are finding it necessary to do more and
more remedial stuff [snorts] because
high schools aren't doing well enough
and the evidence we have I mean it's
it's we are in early days things can
change but the evidence is that AI has
made learning harder in middle schools
and high schools and so that problem is
going to get worse
>> totally if you start using AI for to
solve all the problems and then
university is only going to get worse
then so what should people be doing?
What skills should they be acquiring?
And do you agree with the notion that we
need even more academic knowledge to
acquire those skills? Cuz I'm thinking
about taste and strategic thinking.
>> Absolutely. Because I don't believe true
AGI is just around the corner. I think
we need human creativity more than ever.
And human creativity without strong
foundations is an oxymoron. If anybody
wants my opinion, and I'm not the most
qualified to give you this opinion. I'm
not a mathematician and I'm not a
computer scientist, but if anybody wants
my opinion, I would say go and study
math. Don't be put off by Astra's
solving difficult math problems. We need
human mathematical knowledge. We need
human mathematical maturity. That's
going to be so important. Go and study
physics. Go and study economics. Go and
study engineering. I think those are
going to be great. But also learn
flexibility. I think we're going to need
a lot of flexibility because even within
the same occupation, we will often need
to change what we do as the technology
changes, as the social context changes.
>> So, I think those are really, really
important things. But human ingenuity
and human creativity,
I think, are going to be critical in the
next 10 years.
>> Yeah. And normalizing nonlinear career
is something that resonated with me a
lot. Someone who changed careers
throughout our life. I think this is
going to be our new normal.
>> But then two other principles that I
think are very important and we have
they we should impart starting from
middle school. Learn how to work
alongside and with AI absolutely but
also even more emphasis on civic
responsibility. We have lost in this
country and in most of the rest of the
world a true sense of community and a
true sense of caring for the common good
and working for our collective good and
this is even more important in the age
of AI and that starts with being
informed being engaged
>> that starts with elementary school
really
>> it starts with elementary school I I
yeah I could have extended to elementary
school absolutely we may have encouraged
too much selfishness
We may have encouraged people to draw
into their cocoons via social media and
other things. We may have denigrated
some aspects of community that are
really important. That's also like a
major theme of my new book on what
happened to liberal democracy that we
really need community to be at the
center of a liberal democratic society.
You know, here's what I am not
pessimist. I'm not an [clears throat]
optimist. I'm not but I'm definitely not
a pessimist either. I try to remain
hopeful and two things I find hope in
are that humans are infinitely adaptable
and second even in this polarized
divided world we have very similar
notions of fairness moral shared
understanding on both sides of the
aisle. They just need to come up more
clearly in our communication. And we
need to see the other side not as the
enemy.
>> Even the deepest disagreements [snorts]
should be situated within a context in
which we recognize we're on the same
boat.
>> We're talking about all of this, but
then there comes Dario and says there's
a 25% chance things go really, really
badly with AI. I'm relatively an
optimist. So I think there's a 25%
chance that things go really really
badly and a 75% chance that things go
really really well with with not much uh
not much space.
>> What do you think when you hear this
especially coming from someone who has
to IPO soon and prove that their
technology is very transformational?
>> I think if people in the leading AI labs
are worried about some of the
implications of AI, of course they
should voice that. I welcome and I
applaud their courage to speak, but I am
myself much more worried about a general
sense of loss of control of society over
AI than existential risk as articulated
by Dario or by Elon Musk or uh by
Claxon. Loss of control I'm talking
about is that the general public, the
workers, students, parents lose control
of their own agency
>> because of AI.
Not necessarily
because AI has become super intelligent
and an entity onto itself but partly
because of the way that other companies
or frontier labs are developing AI are
using AI and are rolling out AI. So I am
very worried about loss of control. We
should have that conversation
[clears throat] but we should not ignore
other risks.
>> You have this rating for AI going from
minus 10 to + 10 and you said it was
minus 6. Did it get worse from then? I
think it was 2025 when you gave this
review.
>> No, I actually don't think so because in
2024 2025
I thought there was a lot of damage that
AI could do and I was not clear about
what bottlenecks would [snorts] be
facing us in improving it. I think the
improvements have been fast. So the
dangers have increased but I think the
good things we can do with AI are also
becoming clear. But we just need to
redirect it. We need to steer AI and AI
cannot just be the decision of a handful
of people very smart many of them very
well-meaning people but it's too
important to be left to just a few
people
>> how do you foster that on an individual
level
>> information I think we have to start
with an information and a narrative and
let me tell you
where I think and this is very risky
thing to say because I'm going to say
something negative about the biggest
gatekeepers in our world. But here is my
opinion of which institutions have
failed us worst. The media. Absolutely.
The media. The media has been awful in
cultivating a true sense of information
debate about AI.
For 10 years, it's starting to change
slowly, but very slowly and very
unevenly. for 10 years
either Elon Musk and others like that
could do no wrong and every criticism of
them was just elevating them and
everything about AI was just
fascinating, bewildering, wonderful or
we just talked of like AI as like the
enemy as stoastic parrots or killer
robots. the middle ground where people
could get engaged, could understand the
issues and could actually exercise their
role of stewards of our future as
consumers, as democratic citizens that
was not cultivated. And this is true for
pretty much every organization in the
news media.
>> Let's wrap up with some questions that
are super practical because I want
people to walk away from this with an
action plan, what they can do. First of
all, what do you do with your savings
when you hear all the news or nothing
has changed?
>> Nothing much has changed. I try to have
a balanced portfolio. I think it's very
very difficult to beat the market. I'm
not saying it's impossible, but you need
to be either extremely skilled, spend a
lot of time, or have inside information.
I don't have that much time. I have zero
inside information. I wouldn't want to
have inside information. So, I try to
have a balanced portfolio. Let's jump
into 2035.
If everything goes in a positive way,
what is a typical workday of a knowledge
worker who spends 8 hours by their
computer? Now,
>> great question. I don't know. I can
definitely see a future in which people
would work a few less hours. I could and
still be very productive. I could
definitely see a future, very scary
future in which a lot of people would
not have meaningful work. And I could
definitely see a future in which people
still go to the office or do some
combination of office work and work from
home but differently because of true
complimentary AI but still human
innovation and human talent
are central. I think we live even
leaving AI aside we live at an uniquely
turbulent time. Climate change, aging
population, changing geo geo uh
geopolitical balances, a huge
middle class emerging from the
developing world. All of these require
new goods, new services, new tasks, new
ways of approaching the market, new ways
of organizing companies. And who's going
to do that? Not AI. Humans. And if we
can help those humans be more creative,
amazing. What would be your advice for
someone who sees this amazing wealth
being created by at least what we see in
company's valuations? Uh we still have
to see the ROI on the actual uh the
actual economy. But when you say, you
know, we want to participate in this
goods creation. How can we do that
practically in the next?
>> Look, I I actually don't see how
foundation models are going to make a
lot of money despite all of the
investment going into frontier labs. So,
we'll see some failed IPOs.
>> Not failed IPOs right away because I
think the enthusiasm is there at the
moment, but I really don't see how
you're going to make trillions of
dollars from foundation models because
of potential bottlenecks either in the
development of the models or in their
diffusion. But even if those don't
happen, the next layer of model open
source models are going to be very good
as well. So, it's just not the the
monetization opportunities are going to
be limited. So I think the money is in
highquality data and in applications.
That's where I see the edge. If your
company, your line of business has a lot
of data, cultivate it, use it. Even
build better data, find ways of
capturing that data while also
compensating your workers who are
generating that data.
>> That's fairness. That's also a good
business decision. Think of
applications. That's where going the
edge is going to be. applications are
going to be much harder to replicate by
open source uh if they are really
creative and fill a niche. So I think
those are the places and as a worker
have that flexibility have that
understanding of AI but maintain your
creativity and maintain your base.
>> Yeah. Also for a worker I think it's
also very important to realize that they
are the source of data. They've been
working with customers in the product
for years.
>> And and by the way, this is another
important thing. If you're going to
develop applications, a lot of the tacet
knowledge is with the workers. You can't
just sit in your office in front of a
computer and have been put a very
powerful AI and come up with an
application. You need to go there, get
your hands dirty and talk to workers.
>> Well, hopefully this conversation sparks
some bright ideas and entrepreneurs who
are watching who want to make practical
applications of AI. I want to finish
with the last question. You said
students going to work at AI companies
need a strong moral compass. I think in
general like even as entrepreneur member
of society strong moral compass. Can you
explain what you mean by that?
>> Look, let me give one example from a
different field which is gene editing.
Another amazing technology that has seen
a lot of big advances. But I would say
most people who go into medicine or gene
editing adjacent
occupations
recognize that this is a very morally
ambiguous technology. and many
organizations that have oversight role
from NIH
to the surgeon general and the uh
medical association
have put out general uh ethical
guidelines for gene editing like
germline editing is off right now
because it's just too dangerous we don't
understand it too many risks and etc. So
that's the kind of moral campus that I
think we need in AI as well and we don't
have it. People think of oh I'm doing it
for the good and I completely believe
it. Almost everybody I know who goes
into the field of AI is well-meaning and
they they they want something good for
not just themselves but for society but
there is no clear moral campus and
that's what I'm talking about.
>> It's another interesting conversation
that might
>> hopefully to continue at some point
again. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you so much. It wasn't my
pleasure.